<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd"
 xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/DC/elements/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<control>
	<recordId>NameFiles.S.001</recordId>
    <maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
    <publicationStatus>approved</publicationStatus>
    <maintenanceAgency>
        <agencyCode>ST-In-HSWWA</agencyCode>
        <otherAgencyCode localType="wizlib">H</otherAgencyCode>
        <agencyName>Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry Archives</agencyName>
    </maintenanceAgency>
    <languageDeclaration>
        <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
        <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languageDeclaration>
    <localTypeDeclaration>
        <abbreviation>title</abbreviation>
        <citation xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/wizlib" xlink:title="WizLib Standards" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="new">Standards for Wizarding Libraries and Archives: 2012</citation>
        <descriptiveNote><p>Use within span elements to designate that they are titles.</p></descriptiveNote>
    </localTypeDeclaration>
    <localTypeDeclaration>
        <abbreviation>WizLib</abbreviation>
        <citation xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/wizlib" xlink:title="WizLib Standards" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="new">Standards for Wizarding Libraries and Archives: 2012</citation>
        <descriptiveNote><p>Use to designate that something has been formed in a manner recommended by the WizLib standards.</p></descriptiveNote>
    </localTypeDeclaration>
    <localTypeDeclaration>
        <abbreviation>surname</abbreviation>
        <citation xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/wizlib" xlink:title="WizLib Standards" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="new">Standards for Wizarding Libraries and Archives: 2012</citation>
        <descriptiveNote><p>Use for surnames within part elements.</p></descriptiveNote>
    </localTypeDeclaration>
    <localTypeDeclaration>
        <abbreviation>forename</abbreviation>
        <citation xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/wizlib" xlink:title="WizLib Standards" xlink:actuate="onLoad" xlink:show="new">Standards for Wizarding Libraries and Archives: 2012</citation>
        <descriptiveNote><p>Use for the part of the name which does not involve the surname.</p></descriptiveNote>
    </localTypeDeclaration>
    <maintenanceHistory>
        <maintenanceEvent>
            <eventType>created</eventType>
            <eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-03-09T13:51:42Z">March 9, 2014</eventDateTime>
            <agentType>human</agentType>
            <agent>Felicia Flitwick</agent>
            <eventDescription>This file was created during the final revision process for the finding aid of Slytherin's papers.</eventDescription>
        </maintenanceEvent>
    </maintenanceHistory>
    <sources>
        <source>
            <sourceEntry>Hogwarts: a History</sourceEntry>
            <objectXMLWrap>
                <dublincore>
                    <dc:title>Hogwarts: a History</dc:title>
                    <dc:creator>Bathilda Bagshot</dc:creator>
                    <dc:date>1968</dc:date>
                    <dc:identifier>DA880.B34 1968</dc:identifier>
                </dublincore>
            </objectXMLWrap>
            <descriptiveNote><p>Basic biographical and historical information was taken from <span localType="title">Hogwarts: a History</span>.</p></descriptiveNote>
        </source>
    </sources>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
    <identity>
        <entityId>S.001</entityId>
        <entityType>person</entityType>
        <nameEntry localType="WizLib">
            <part localType="surname">Slytherin</part>
            <part localType="forename">Salazar</part>
            <part>d. circa 1100</part>
            <authorizedForm>WizLib</authorizedForm>
        </nameEntry>
    </identity>
    <description>
        <existDates>
            <dateRange>
                <fromDate notAfter="0950" standardDate="0950">before 950</fromDate>
                <toDate notAfter="1100" standardDate="1100">before 1100</toDate>
            </dateRange>
        </existDates>
        <places>
            <place>
                <placeRole>birth</placeRole>
                <placeEntry>fens, England</placeEntry>
                <descriptiveNote><p>It is uncertain in which fen Slytherin was born, but this information about his origin has been preserved in Hogwarts house lore.</p></descriptiveNote>
            </place>
            <place>
                <placeRole>residence</placeRole>
                <placeEntry vocabularySource="WizLib">Hogwarts (Scotland)</placeEntry>
                <descriptiveNote><p>Slytherin resided at the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry from the time of its founding until his schism with other founders and departure.</p></descriptiveNote>
            </place>
        </places>
        <occupations>
            <occupation>
                <term vocabularySource="WizLib">wizard</term>
            </occupation>
            <occupation>
                <term vocabularySource="WizLib">parselmouth</term>
            </occupation>
            <occupation>
                <term vocabularySource="WizLib">legilimens</term>
            </occupation>
            <occupation>
                <term vocabularySource="WizLib">basilisk-breeder</term>
            </occupation>
            <occupation>
                <term vocabularySource="WizLib">professor</term>
            </occupation>
        </occupations>
        <structureOrGenealogy>
            <p>Known descendents of Salazar Slytherin:</p>
            <list>
                <item>Corvinus Gaunt (18th century)</item>
                <item>Marvolo Gaunt (19th-20th century)</item>
                <item>Morfin Gaunt (20th century)</item>
                <item>Merope Gaunt (1907 - 31 December, 1926)</item>
                <item>Tom Malvolo Riddle (31 December, 1926 - 2 May, 1998)  </item>
            </list>
        </structureOrGenealogy>
        <generalContext>
            <p>Salazar Slytherin was born in an era before the formalized teaching of magic began. As a founder of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, he was an influential force on the development of magical education. Slytherin is best remembered for favoring students of magical bloodlines. One of the four houses at the school is named for him. In the 20th century, his half-muggle heir, Tom Malvolo Riddle (Lord Voldemort) would upend the world of British Wizardry by inciting both Wizarding Wars.</p>
        </generalContext>
        <biogHist>
            <abstract>Salazar Slytherin was a pure-blood wizard born in the first half of the tenth century. He is one of the four founders of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, where one of the four modern houses is named after him. After an argument with the other founders of Hogwarts, particularly Godric Gryffindor, Slytherin left the school. It is unknown where he died, but evidence suggests that his date of death was before the twelfth century.</abstract>
            <p>Salazar Slytherin was born in the first half of the tenth century, somewhere in fen-country England. Researchers believe it was likely Norfolk, Lincolnshire, or Cambridgeshire, but may have been a connected-county. He came from a family of pure-blood wizards, although the names of his parents are not recorded. It is unknown whether he trained at a school of the time, at home, or under a master. Together with Gryffindor, Ravenclaw, and Hufflepuff, he founded the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry.</p>
            <p>At Hogwarts, Slytherin taught Legilimency, the magical art of forming a mental connection with another's mind and extracting information or interacting with their thought processes. This may have been a genetic talent, as his descendent, Tom Riddle, was also a noted legilimens. Slytherin was also a Parselmouth, a known genetic trait, and able to speak with snakes. He bred at least one basilisk, which he left at Hogwarts in the Chamber of Secrets. The Chamber remained unopened until 1943, when Riddle opened it and used the basilisk to attack Muggle-borns. The basilisk was not killed until 1993.</p>
            <p>Slytherin believed that the school should only teach pure-blood students and should definitely not accept students whose parents were both Muggles. His own house, Slytherin, continued this tradition, but the other founders overruled him. After an argument with Godric Gryffindor, which may have involved a duel, Slytherin left the school.</p>
            <p>While it is not known when or where Slytherin died, his spellbooks were recovered shortly before the turn of the twelfth century by Slytherin alumnus and professor Albert Shallowheart. It is assumed that Slytherin was dead when these books were recovered. The books remained in Slytherin house until after the first Wizarding War, when they were donated to the Hogwarts Archives.</p>
        </biogHist>
    </description>
    <relations>
        <cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/hogwarts-cpf/NameFiles.H.001.xml">
            <relationEntry>Hufflepuff, Helga</relationEntry>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Co-founder of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry. While not the most combative, her acceptance of all students willing to learn was the most at odds with Slytherin's pure blood philosophy.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </cpfRelation>
        <cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/hogwarts-cpf/NameFiles.G.001.xml">
            <relationEntry>Gryffindor, Godric</relationEntry>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Co-founder of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry. Initially a good friend and correspondent of Salazar Slytherin, Gryffindor later cut ties over their disagreement concerning acceptance of muggle-born students.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </cpfRelation>
        <cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/hogwarts-cpf/NameFiles.R.001.xml">
            <relationEntry>Ravenclaw, Rowena</relationEntry>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Co-founder of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </cpfRelation>
        <resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://eadiva.com/hogwarts-ead/SL.0001.xml">
            <relationEntry>Manuscripts of Salazar Slytherin</relationEntry>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>This collection at the Hogwarts archives contains Slytherin's correspondence, known spell books, journals, and other scrolls.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </resourceRelation>
    </relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>
